<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R on DATA606 - Fall 2020</title>
    <link>/categories/r/</link>
    <description>Recent content in R on DATA606 - Fall 2020</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Colors</title>
      <link>/post/2020-03-03-colors/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2020-03-03-colors/</guid>
      <description>Upon grading the labs I noticed there is interest in adding color to the plots. I understand and appreciate the desire to make your figures more aesthetically pleasing. I have used colors to make the figures fit the overall style of whatever publication they are going to be used in. However, my general advice is to only use color when it adds value. For example, coloring bars or points based upon a quantitative variable is often very helpful.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Random Numbers and Seeds in R</title>
      <link>/post/2020-01-29-random_numbers_and_seeds/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2020-01-29-random_numbers_and_seeds/</guid>
      <description>To explore how R generates randome numbers, we will use the rnorm function. This function draws a random number from a normal distribution with a mean = 0 and standard deviation = 1 (though these can be changed with the mean and sd parameters). With n = 1 we will get two random numbers.
rnorm(n = 1) ## [1] 1.091666 rnorm(n = 1) ## [1] -1.530402 Each time you run the command you will get a different number.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting Started with R</title>
      <link>/post/2020-01-20-getting-started-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2020-01-20-getting-started-with-r/</guid>
      <description>To get started with the labs, you will need to install R and other supporting applications. Links to download all the software is on the Software page at http://data606.net/software which is available on the Course Overview menu. Once you are in RStudio, you will need to install a number of R packages using the following two commands:
install.packages(c(&amp;#39;openintro&amp;#39;,&amp;#39;OIdata&amp;#39;,&amp;#39;devtools&amp;#39;,&amp;#39;tidyverse&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;ggplot2&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;psych&amp;#39;,&amp;#39;reshape2&amp;#39;,&amp;#39;knitr&amp;#39;,&amp;#39;markdown&amp;#39;,&amp;#39;shiny&amp;#39;,&amp;#39;R.rsp&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;fivethirtyeight&amp;#39;)) devtools::install_github(&amp;quot;jbryer/DATA606&amp;quot;) Note that this course used to be listed as IS 606, hence the different package name.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>